Peter C. Bunnell Papers, circa 1857-2018 (bulk 1960-2018): Finding Aid C1629
Manuscripts Division
Peter C. Bunnell Papers
1960-2018
1857-2018
Manuscripts Division
Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.)
Princeton University. Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections
Bunnell, Peter C.
C1629
105 boxes
This collection consists of the papers of photography historian, professor, author, and curator Peter C. Bunnell, spanning his student and professional career from the 1950s to 2018. Materials include subject files, correspondence, photographs, publications and drafts of publications, among other items.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of materials relating to Peter C. Bunnell's work as a historian and professor of photography, an author, and an active member of organizations related to photography. The bulk of the collection includes subject files, which cover photographic topics, photographers, students, lectures, photography collections, galleries or museums, and organizations related to photography. The materials in these files include press releases, exhibition announcements, and other exhibition promotional material; typewritten and handwritten notes; correspondence with photographers and colleagues from various institutions; copy prints and negatives; organizational memos, meeting minutes, and agendas; and journal articles and news clippings. A significant part of Bunnell's files throughout his career focused on Minor White, Clarence H. White, Alfred Stieglitz, and Ansel Adams, but many modern photographers are represented. Subject files from his involvement in several institutions over the course of his career include the Museum of Modern Art and the George Eastman House, among others.
The correspondence files span Bunnell's time as a student and throughout his career. Major correspondents include Ruth Bernhard, Jerry Uelsmann, Ansel Adams, Paul Strand, and Van Deren Coke.
The rest of the collection includes file groups dedicated to the Friends of Photography and the Society for Photographic Education, which include memos, meeting minutes, agendas, correspondence, newsletters, policies and procedures, and financial reports; drafts and final versions of publications that Bunnell wrote or edited, including A Photographic Vision: Pictorial Photography, 1889–1923 (1980) and Aperture Magazine Anthology: The Minor White Years, 1952–1976 (2012); and photographs from Bunnell's retirement dinner in 2002.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged into seven file groups, maintaining original order. Materials related to a certain person or organization are often found across several series.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research with the exception of files containing student records, which are closed for 75 years from the date of creation. All material in the Subject Files must be reviewed for student records prior to research use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Peter C. Bunnell in April 2019 (AM 2019-109).
Appraisal
No materials were removed from the collection during 2019 processing beyond routine appraisal practices.
Related Materials
Princeton University Art Museum. Princeton, NJ. Minor White and Clarence H. White Correspondence.
Bunnell, Peter C.
Biographical / Historical
Peter C. Bunnell is a historian of modern photography and the McAlpin Professor of the History of Photography and Modern Art Emeritus at Princeton University. He was born in Poughkeepsie, New York, in 1937. Bunnell attended the Rochester Institute of Technology for his undergraduate degree. He then went on to receive graduate degrees from Ohio University in 1961 and Yale University in 1965. During his years in school, Bunnell worked at the George Eastman House in Rochester, New York, at Aperture Magazine with Minor White, and the Alfred Stieglitz Archive at Yale. Bunnell began working at the Museum of Modern Art in 1966 and was appointed Curator of the Department of Photography in 1970.
Bunnell began his professorship at Princeton in 1972 and retired in 2002. While at Princeton, Bunnell took on several roles at the Princeton University Art Museum between 1973 and 2000: Director, Acting Director, and Curator of Photography. Also during this time, Bunnell served on the Board of Directors of the Society for Photographic Education and the Board of Trustees for the Friends of Photography, a nonprofit founded in part by Ansel Adams. He was also involved in other visiting committees, associations, and activities related to photography.
Modern photography; Photography--History.; Photography Exhibitions.; Museums--Curatorship.; Princeton University--Faculty; Friends of Photography; Society for photographic education; George Eastman House; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); Princeton university art museum; Adams, Ansel, 1902-1984; Stieglitz, Alfred, 1864-1946.; Uelsmann, Jerry, 1934-
- Subject Files, 1857-2018; 70 boxes
  Arrangement
  Materials are in original order, which is largely alphabetical. Files towards the end of the grouping do not maintain alphabetical order and were likely kept separately by the creator.
  Scope and Contents
  This file group includes materials related to Bunnell's work in organizations such as the George Eastman House, Museum of Modern Art (MoMA), Princeton University Art Museum (PUAM), among others; his teaching at Princeton and guest lectures; his publications and exchanges with publishers; his research on photographers and photography; his time as a student at Yale University and Ohio University; and his appraisal work. The bulk of the materials are exhibition brochures, press releases, and postcards; newspaper and magazine clippings; and photocopies of journal, newspaper, and magazine articles. Other types of materials include handwritten notes regarding research material or classes; student dissertations; typewritten notes about phone calls, conversations, interviews, or exhibitions attended; correspondence regarding projects, publications, and student advisements; copy prints and negatives of photographs sent to Bunnell for collection consideration; and photographs and negatives of exhibitions.
  Notable headings with significant material include Richard Avedon, Ruth Bernhard, Manuel Álvarez Bravo, Harry Callahan, Paul Caponigro, Henri Cartier-Bresson, Walter Chappell, Carl Chiarenza, Alvin Langdon Coburn, Imogen Cunningham, Thomas Cooper, Judy Dater, Bruce Davidson, Roy DeCarava, Michael de Courcy, Abe Frajndlich, Focus Gallery (San Francisco), Lee Friedlander, Peter Galassi, Laura Gilpin, Emmet Gowin, Robert Heinecken, Eikoh Hosoe, Gertrude Käsebier, Michael Kenna, George Platt Lynes, Pradip Malde, Roger Mayne, David McAlpin Collection, Metroplitan Museum of Art, Barbara Morgan, Beaumont Newhall, Jon O'Neal, John Pfahl, Princeton University Art Museum, Samuel W. Samore, Fazal Sheikh, Naomi Savage, Aaron Siskind, Frederick Sommer, Edward Steichen, Paul Strand, Tomatsu Shomei, Jerry Uelsmann, Max Waldman, Marta Weiss, Lynton Wells, Edward Weston, and Lee Witkin.
  Conditions Governing Access
  All material in the Subject Files must be reviewed for student records prior to research use. Please submit requests for material at least 10 business days before visiting the library to allow time for this review. An archivist will respond within 10 business days to let you know whether it is available for research use. Individuals may make up to 15 requests per month.
  - Aarons, Slim - Affarian, Carl, circa 1960-2011; 1 box (Box 1)
  - African Photography/Marta Weiss Paper - Aperture Panel: "Inside the Photography Gallery", circa 1944-2012; 1 box (Box 2)
  - Apfelbaum, Sally - Art Institute of Chicago, circa 1964-2018; 1 box (Box 3)
  - The Art Journal (London) - Bailly-Maître-Grand, Patrick, circa 1963-2018; 1 box (Box 4)
  - Baldessari, John - Eileen Berger, circa 1970-2012; 1 box (Box 5)
  - John Berger - Bockelberg Collection, circa 1971-2010; 1 box (Box 6)
  - Bunnell: Distinguished Teaching Award - Brazilian Photographers, circa 1962-2002; 1 box (Box 7)
  - Kate Breakey - Los Angeles Reading, Jan. '98, circa 1971-2013; 1 box (Box 8)
  - Cambridge University Press - Canadian Centre for Architecture, circa 1974-2015; 1 box (Box 9)
  - Canadian Museum of Contemporary Photography - Henri Cartier-Bresson, circa 1962-2017; 1 box (Box 10)
  - Henri Cartier-Bresson/Carlton Willers Correspondence - Carl Chiarenza, circa 1976-2010; 1 box (Box 11)
  - Carl Chiarenza - Ernest Cole, circa 1979-2014; 1 box (Box 12)
  - Coleman, Allen - Cookman, Claude (Henri Cartier-Bresson Dissertation), circa 1962-2014; 1 box (Box 13)
  - Claude Cookman - Imogen Cunningham, circa 1961-2009; 1 box (Box 14)
  - Cunningham, Imogen - DeCamp, Michael, circa 1968-2005; 1 box (Box 15)
  - DeCarava, Roy - Nell Dorr, circa 1964-2014; 1 box (Box 16)
  - Dossi, Ugo - Marion Ettlinger, circa 1973-2014; 1 box (Box 17)
  - European Photography - Susan Fenton, circa 1966-2007; 1 box (Box 18)
  - Fentress, Sam - Abe Frajndlich: Minor White Book '81, circa 1970-2014; 1 box (Box 19)
  - Frampton, Hollis - Futurist Photography, circa 1960-2014; 1 box (Box 20)
  - Marc Gaede - Gilpin, Laura (Estate), circa 1968-2003; 1 box (Box 21)
  - Gilson, Jean-Pierre - Greenfield, Lois, circa 1989-2002; 1 box (Box 22)
  - Greenfield-Sanders, Timothy - G. Ray Hawkins Gallery, circa 1961-2014; 1 box (Box 23)
  - G. Ray Hawkins Gallery - Michael Hoffman, circa 1958-2009; 1 box (Box 24)
  - Hogan, Melissa (& Amblard, Patrick) (P. M. Hoblargen) - The Influence of Photography on Painting, 19th Century, circa 1962-2004; 1 box (Box 25)
  - The Influence of Photography of Painting, 19th Century - André Jammes, circa 1962-2012; 1 box (Box 26)
  - Jammes/Dougan Collection 19th Century Symposium - Gertrude Käsebier, circa 1975-2014; 1 box (Box 27)
  - Gertrude Käsebier - Eastman Kodak Co. (George Eastman), circa 1976-2012; 1 box (Box 28)
  - Kodak Company - Lartigue Jacques-Henri, circa 1961-2015; 1 box (Box 29)
  - Latana - Light Factory, Inc., circa 1964-2014; 1 box (Box 30)
  - Light Gallery - Lynes, George Platt, circa 1964-2006; 1 box (Box 31)
  - Lyon, Danny - Mapplethorpe, Robert, circa 1958-2013; 1 box (Box 32)
  - Robert Mapplethorpe - Meatyard, Ralph Eugene, circa 1972-2013; 1 box (Box 33)
  - François Méchain - Yukio Mishima, circa 1964-2018; 1 box (Box 34)
  - Leonard Misonne - Barbara Morgan Archive, UCLA, circa 1966-2011; 1 box (Box 35)
  - Margaret Morgan - MoMA: Expansion and Reopening, circa 1943-2011; 1 box (Box 36)
  - MoMA Exhibitions Directed, 1967, Recent Acquisition Photography - Mutter, Scott, circa 1962-2016; 1 box (Box 37)
  - Eadweard Muybridge - New Republic article "Why Photography Now," October 29, 1977, circa 1952-2003; 1 box (Box 38)
  - New School for Social Research - Otten, Hanno, circa 1974-2001; 1 box (Box 39)
  - Otto, Eberhard - Petricone, Paul, circa 1967-2014; 1 box (Box 40)
  - Petry, Richard - Photography Instructors Association, circa 1959-2014; 1 box (Box 41)
  - Photography Instructors Association - Barbara Pollack, circa 1960-2009; 1 box (Box 42)
  - Pollock, Jackson - Princeton University Art Museum, Photography at Princeton Exhibition '98, circa 1970-2013; 1 box (Box 43)
  - Princeton University Art Museum Photography Committee Proposal - Rejlander: Princeton Album (2002), circa 1975-2011; 1 box (Box 44)
  - Rejlander: Moderna Musset, Stockholm - Rome, Stuart, circa 1857-2003; 1 box (Box 45)
  - Violet Romer (Weston Sitter) - Salt Print, circa 1974-2006; 1 box (Box 46)
  - Britt Salvesen - Seattle Art Museum Lecture, '78, circa 1974-2001; 1 box (Box 47)
  - Paul Seawright - Sinsabaugh/Illinois Reports, circa 1961-2014; 1 box (Box 48)
  - Sipley Collection - Jack Smith, circa 1965-1999; 1 box (Box 49)
  - Joel Smith - Sonneborn, Barbara, circa 1969-2013; 1 box (Box 50)
  - Eve Sonneman - Steichen Estate Appraisal, circa 1960-2008; 1 box (Box 51)
  - Steichen Estate Appraisal - Struth, Thomas, circa 1965-2010; 1 box (Box 52)
  - Roy Stryker, Farm Security Administration - Taylor Dissertation, circa 1962-2017; 1 box (Box 53)
  - Teaching Films/Photography - Ueda Shoji, circa 1973-2017; 1 box (Box 54)
  - Uelsmann, Jerry - Victorian Photography, circa 1958-2013; 1 box (Box 55)
  - Video-tape - Mike Weaver, The Photographic Art Exhibition, 1985, circa 1963-2014; 1 box (Box 56)
  - Webb, Boyd - Weston, Daybooks, Miscellaneous Quotes, circa 1958-2003; 1 box (Box 57)
  - Edward Weston: Exhibition Notices - Witkin, Joel-Peter, circa 1946-2008; 1 box (Box 58)
  - Lee Witkin - Zaburov, Boris, circa 1961-2012; 1 box (Box 59)
  - Amir Zaki - Zwillinger, Rhonda, circa 1953-2003; 1 box (Box 60)
  - Aaron Siskind Reference Material, circa 1945-1996; 1 box (Box 60)
  - Oxford University Press City Book, 1970-1971; 1 box (Box 67)
  - Uelsmann Aperture Monograph - 2nd Edition, 1970-1973; 1 box (Box 67)
  - Uelsmann Morgan + Morgan Monograph, 1975-1982; 1 box (Box 67)
  - Lynton Wells Catalogue Files, 1970-1979; 1 box (Box 67)
  - Weston Doubleday Portfolio, 1970; 1 box (Box 67)
  - Weston Anthology Files, 1982-1983; 2 boxes (Box 67, Box 68)
  - Yale Course Notes, 1961-1963; 1 box (Box 67)
  - Eastman House, circa 1950-1994; 1 box (Box 68)
  - Arno Press Files - Series I + II, 1971-1980; 1 box (Box 69)
  - American Federation of Arts Program Committee, 1976-1984; 1 box (Box 69)
  - International Exhibitions Committee, 1976-1979; 1 box (Box 69)
  - College Art Association Board, 1972-1979; 1 box (Box 69)
  - Boston University - Board of Advisors, 1976-1979; 1 box (Box 69)
  - MoMA Curatorial Files, 1967-1972; 1 box (Box 70)
  - Alfred Stieglitz Research Files, circa 1877-2013; 6 boxes (Box 61, Box 62, Box 63, Box 64, Box 65, Box 66)
    Materials related to Bunnell's research on American photographer Alfred Stieglitz, whom Bunnell wrote his Yale dissertation on; however, materials are from throughout Bunnell's career. Materials include correspondence with other researchers, museums, and collectors; dissertations and student papers; and photocopied and original articles by and about Stieglitz. Hand- and typewritten notes and copied archival correspondence seems to have come from archival research on the Stieglitz collections at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. Files on contemporaries of Alfred Stieglitz, such as Georgia O'Keefe, can also be found in this file grouping.
    The materials are in original, alphabetical order by folder title. Folders are titled with people's names, publication or project titles, organizations, and general categories, such as "Exhibition" or "Article."
- Teaching Materials, 1970-2007; 4 boxes
  The materials are in original order. The course and seminar materials are arranged first in chronological order and then by course number; the other related teaching materials do not appear to have a specified order.
  This file group contains materials related to Bunnell's teaching, mostly at Princeton University, but also for guest lectures and seminars at other colleges and universities. Materials include syllabi; course rosters and grades; course evaluations; course listings; assignment feedback; and notes for lectures.
  This material is restricted until 75 years from the date of creation due to the presence of student records.
  - History of Photography Class Materials, 1989-2001; 1 box (Box 71)
  - Undergraduate and Graduate Course and Seminar Files, 1970-1984; 1 box (Box 72)
  - Undergraduate and Graduate Course and Seminar Files, 1985-1999; 1 box (Box 73)
  - Undergraduate and Graduate Course and Seminar Files, 1999-2002; 1 box (Box 74)
  - Other Related Teaching Materials, 1974-2007; 1 box (Box 74)
    These materials include files on senior and graduate theses; public lecture notes and slide lists; History of Photography program and professorship files; and articles that Bunnell set aside for possible assigned reading.
- Friends of Photography Records, 1967-2004; 6 boxes
  This collection is open for research with the exception of files containing student records, which are closed for 75 years from the date of creation. All material in the Subject Files must be reviewed for student records prior to research use.
  The materials are in original, largely chronological, order.
  This file group includes materials related to Bunnell's involvement with the Friends of Photography. Materials related to his work on the Board of Trustees include meeting agendas; memos; financial reports; handwritten notes; correspondence; reports; and mailers to members. Materials cover development campaigns, such as the Ansel Adams Center Campaign, special committee meetings, annual meetings, membership, and studies on the Friends of Photography's program and workshop offerings. Also included in this series are Friends of Photography Newsletters from 1978 to 2000.
  - Board of Trustees Materials, 1967-1982; 1 box (Box 75)
  - Ansel Adams Center Campaign, 1983-1986; 1 box (Box 76)
  - Board of Trustees Materials, 1986-1988; 1 box (Box 77)
  - Board of Trustees Materials, 1987-2000; 1 box (Box 78)
  - Friends of Photography Newsletters, 1978-2000; 1 box (Box 78)
  - Board of Trustees and End of Term Materials, 1970-2001; 1 box (Box 79)
  - Board of Trustees and End of Term Materials, 1983-2004; 1 box (Box 80)
- Society for Photographic Education Records, 1962-2017; 5 boxes
  These materials are in original, largely chronological, order. Box 85 is made up of Society for Photographic Education material that Bunnell moved from the Research Files to this series and is not in strict chronological order.
  This file group includes materials related to Bunnell's work on the Board of Directors of the Society for Photographic Education, as well as his general membership and involvement. Materials include conference agendas and reports; correspondence; policies and procedures manuals; membership guidelines; and legal and incorporation documents. Other materials include brochures Bunnell picked up at conferences; Exposure magazine from 1968 to 1984; the Society for Photographic Education Newsletter from 1984-1988; membership directories and conference announcements; and other newsletters.
  - Board of Directors Materials, 1962-1974; 1 box (Box 81)
  - Board of Directors Materials, 1975-1981; 1 box (Box 82)
  - Board of Directors Materials, 1981-1994; 1 box (Box 83)
  - Board of Directors Materials, 1966-1982; 1 box (Box 84)
  - Exposure Magazine and Society for Photographic Education Newsletters, 1968-1988; 1 box (Box 84)
  - Membership Directories, Conference Announcements, and Newsletters, 1995-2017; 1 box (Box 85)
- Correspondence, 1948-2018; 11 boxes
  This file group includes correspondence from colleagues, publishers, and friends. Also consult the Subject Files for files on people and organizations included here, which may also include correspondence.
  The correspondence is in original order, which is made up of two groupings: Chronological and Alphabetical.
  - Chronological, 1956-2018; 8 boxes
    This correspondence includes letters and postcards from friends and colleagues. Some correspondents with significant material include Richard Kollath, Gary Cox, Anne Earley, Eric Anderson, Carl Chiarenza, and James Alinder.
    This file group of correspondence is arranged chronologically and within each year, correspondents are arranged alphabetically.
    - Correspondence, 1956-1965; 1 box (Box 86)
    - Correspondence, 1966-1971; 1 box (Box 87)
    - Correspondence, 1972-1976; 1 box (Box 88)
    - Correspondence, 1977-1983; 1 box (Box 89)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1991; 1 box (Box 90)
    - Correspondence, 1992-1997; 1 box (Box 91)
    - Correspondence, 1998-2003; 1 box (Box 92)
    - Correspondence, 2004-2018; 1 box (Box 93)
  - Alphabetical, 1948-2018; 3 boxes
    This correspondence is arranged alphabetically.
    This correspondence includes letters and postcards from people significant to Bunnell's work. Typewritten summaries of phone calls and in-person visits are also included in these files. Notable correspondents include Ansel Adams, Georgia O'Keeffe, Van Deren Coke, Beaumont Newhall, Abe Frajndlich, and Paul Strand. Some of the Ansel Adams correspondence are copies of others' correspondence with Adams.
    - Ansel Adams Correspondence, 1958-1983; 1958-2008; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 1)
    - Ansel Adams, Moonrise Acquisition by McAlpin, PCB, etc., 1948-2010; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 2)
    - Ansel Adams Moonrise Conservation, 2007-2010; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 3)
    - Virginia Adams (Anne Adams Helms), 1989-2012; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 4)
    - Ruth Bernhard and Others Correspondence with Peter C. Bunnell, 1975-2006; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 5)
    - Bourdeau, Robert, 1960-2013; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 6)
    - William Bowen, 1973-1977; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 7)
    - Doris Bry, 1961-1976; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 8)
    - Christenberry, Bill, 1971-1977; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 9)
    - Coke, Van Deren, 1970-1977; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 10)
    - Edwards, Hugh, 1961-1969; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 11)
    - Abe Frajndlich, 1976-1983; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 12)
    - Greenough, Sarah, 1984-2002; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 13)
    - Natasha Lyons, 1961-1979; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 14)
    - Grace Mayer, Museum of Modern Art, 1959-1996; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 15)
    - Beaumont Newhall, 1959-1993; 2 folders (Box B-001326, Folder 16-17)
    - Norman, Dorothy, 1959-2006; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 18)
    - O'Keefe: Peter C. Bunnell Personal/Letters/Visits, 1960-1985; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 19)
    - Oxford University Press, 1967-1975; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 20)
    - Oxford Companion, 1976-1978; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 21)
    - Peregrine Smith, Inc., 1984-1987; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 22)
    - Peregrine Smith, Inc. Pictorialism Post-Publication, 1981-1985; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 23)
    - Peregrine Smith, Inc. Pictorialism Publication, 1978-1980; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 24)
    - Polaroid Corporation, 1964-1975; 1 folder (Box B-001326, Folder 25)
    - Joe Rauch, 1989-2015; 27 folders (Box B-001326, Folder 26-30, Box B-001327, Folder 1-22)
    - Neil Rudenstine, 1977; 1 folder (Box B-001327, Folder 23)
    - Richard Rudisill, 1967-2004; 1 folder (Box B-001327, Folder 24)
    - William Schaaf, 1970-2017; 8 folders (Box B-001327, Folder 25-32)
    - Scharf, Aaron, 1966-1969; 1 folder (Box B-001327, Folder 33)
    - Strand, Paul, 1960-1975; 1 folder (Box B-001327, Folder 34)
    - Trachtenberg, Alan, 1967-1992; 1 folder (Box B-001327, Folder 35)
    - Jerry Uelsmann: Preface Texts and Drafts for Book Other Realities, 2004-2005; 1 folder (Box B-001327, Folder 36)
    - Jerry Uelsmann: Professor Award '96; Retirement '98; Fellowship Endowment '12; Honorary Degree '12, 1996-2012; 1 folder (Box B-001327, Folder 37)
    - Uelsmann, Jerry, 1964-2018; 6 folders (Box B-001327, Folder 38-41, Box B-001328, Folder 1-2)
    - Jerry Uelsmann Correspondence on Miscellaneous Photographs, 1967-1976; 1 folder (Box B-001328, Folder 3)
    - Carlton Willers, 2004-2016; 2 folders (Box B-001328, Folder 4-5)
- Writings, 1960-2017; 10 boxes
  These materials are in original order.
  This file group includes published and unpublished works Bunnell wrote, edited, reviewed, and/or contributed to. Also consult the Subject Files for files on publications included here, which may include drafts and other materials related to these publications.
  - Publications, 1960-2017; 8 boxes (Box B-001328, Box 97, Box 98, Box 99, Box 100, Box 101, Box 102, Box 103)